Jack: So, what is meant when we talk
about Imperative and Declarative coding?
Leah: Imperative coding or programming
can directly change the ‘State’
of the program through statements
which provide instructions, or
anything in the memory that holds
the current values of your program.
Imperative statements are grouped into
sections which are called procedures.
When called, a procedure will run
the input through a set of statements
and return an output or change the
program to the desired ‘state’.
Jack: For example, let’s say we
have a data structure containing
individual student grades,
and which class they are in.
We then want to extract
all grades from Class C.
An Imperative procedure might express
[in code] the following statements:
1.
Create a new variable called ‘Class
C results’ to collect results
2.
Go through one student at a
time, and check the following:
3.
Is the student in Class C
4.
If they are, add their
grades to ‘Class C results’
5.
If they are not, move to the next
student and continue this procedure
until all have been checked
Leah: Because imperative source
code can be low-level, we use
procedures to make a step towards
higher-level declarative programming.
Let’s look at an example of this in code.
Now let’s look at Declarative
coding or programming.
Most forms of Declarative
programming do not support change
to the ‘State’ of a program.
The programs are run based on a
series of ‘expressions’ which specify
exactly what the program should
accomplish, rather than how it does it.
This is accomplished through
logical statements, or those
that describe the function.
Let’s go back to our example which
contains student grades and classes.
We want to achieve the same result as
before, ‘extract all grades from Class C’.
Our declarative statement may be more
direct, for example saying [in code]:
Jack: EXTRACT all grades from
students in Class C and ADD them
to a new variable ‘Class_C_results’
The output is the same as with imperative
programming, but the result was achieved
with an expression of what the results
should be, not how to get them, as
this is implicit in the program.
Now let’s look at an
example of this in code.